foreign
welcome back to another name tutorial
in this tutorial we'll be talking about
if statements if statements are used to
add logic to your program you can make
your program make decisions for example
when you go to the store and you're like
hmm
should I buy
the bar one
or the lunch bar
that's a choice you have to make you can
even write a program to make that choice
for you
and this is where programming really
starts to become incredibly powerful
not only to cover all of these in a
physical manner so I'm just going to
give them all to you right now so these
are all the type of operations you can
do larger than lesser than larger than
equal
lesser than or equal
you also have equal not equal and we'll
use a few of them to give you an example
and then finally
and
or not
as well as xor and we'll get into what
all of these does except for xor this
basically returns true if one of the
conditions are false and the other is
true
which can be useful if you have a
scenario for it
all right so let's declare a few
variables
so we have age is equal to 24
name is equal to Jack
and birthday
is equal to true
cool so we have an integer age a string
Jack and a Boolean yes or no true
cool now let's say we have a bar now
let's first say if someone is under the
age of 21 they are not allowed to enter
this bar then we can check if their age
is less than 21. then Echo you may not
enter
or enter
so here we're checking if this variable
age is less than 21 we could have even
put a normal number here like 24 that's
perfectly fine anyhow so we're checking
is this less than this if it is Princess
let's make the age 10 for now
if we run this
we will get you may not enter
but if we were to say 21 because this is
any checking for less than 21. so 21 and
older is perfectly fine so if we run
this you'll see we don't get an output
so just by using an if statement we've
told our program to only do something if
it meets a specific condition
now let's say if someone's too old
they're also not allowed to enter so we
can say if age
is more than 60 so if they're older than
then you should tell them
Echo
you are elderly
may not
enter
cool so now we have two if statements
here and take note of the indentation
here that's actually important if you
just do this it might for an error at
you indentation is important
so you'll also notice here this is not
part of this top F statement because
there's no indentation here the
indentation and Nim is very important so
all of this is part of this if statement
but this is not part of this top if
statement because it is unindicted
always take note of your indentation if
you know if you're coming from python
it's the same concept what is indented
is important
all right
so now that we know that that this if
statement does not contain the save
statement they will run independently so
we were to go 20 this bottom one will
execute but not this top one
run it you may not enter
and here we will be saying
610 then the top one will execute but
not the bottom one
your elderly may not enter
now let's say if they are not one of
these two ages
they are allowed to enter because then
you can just say Echo
you may enter
but now we have a problem
we will now have to if we want to make
this one only executive D's are not true
we have to Dango if
H is more or equal to 21
or age is more equal to 60
or not more equal but I mean less or
equal to 60. then you may enter so now
we have three if statements one for if
they're older than 60 one if they're
younger than 21 and one if they're older
or the same age as 21
or younger or the same age as 60.
if we run this and let's say our guy is
32. now they are allowed to enter
because they are not older than 60 and
not younger than 21.
so if this or statement here we can
check if this is true
or if this is true and you can use
brackets to make it a little bit easier
because now you can see this goes first
then this it checks them so if either of
these
is true then this will execute but now
we have a problem
what if we were to say they are 302
will actually get your elderly may not
enter as well as you may enter
because all checks every one of these
two are true not if both are true
so if this is a True Value but this is a
false value
this will still execute because this one
is true so if yes
or no that's what you're basically
saying here so if either of these two
are yes true then print this out
if we were to say and instead then we'll
say if this is true and if this is true
then execute this so now we were to run
this we'll get your elderly may not
enter
but if we were to say 31 now
then we will not get that we'll just get
you may enter and if we were to make
them 18
then you may not enter cool so we have
just covered larger than larger than or
equal less than lesser than or equal
and and or
all right
now we can actually make this a little
bit less to work with for example we can
say alif and now these two are one if
statement but this one checks if this
executes
then this will not execute
if this does not execute then we'll try
and execute this but they cannot both be
executed at the same time to give an
example let's say we have this if
statement
and here we're saying after age
is less than
or actually let's go here let's say if
their age is more than 18 right just
ignore this piece of text here and if
your age is less than 21
now if we were to go here and we would
just say 20. so it will fill both of
these categories
we run it
then you get both of these values
however
if we were to say
L if which means else if
then only one of them can execute at a
time your elderly may not enter and the
one that executes is the one that gets
hit first so if we were to say
10. this one will not execute because 10
is less than 18. but this one will
execute so now if we run this you get
you may not enter
so just as an example that allows us to
have two if statements that does not get
in conflict with each other only one of
those two if statements can run
you can of course have as many else if
statements as you want you don't have
any limits but take note if one of them
gets executed the rest will be ignored
and take note all them should preferably
have a different value so this could be
22 23 24 25 and so on and so forth and
didn't all need to check age
one could check age the other one could
maybe check the name so here we could
say I'll say if name is equal to
Mike then you may not enter and that's
the wrong equal there that should be two
equals
I will get into that in a second
okay so now that we know that we can
actually use this to our advantage
now we have this if statement here at
the bottom the problem with this if
statement is every time we want to add
another check here we have to add it
here as well
but because if statements are so
powerful we can add in else statement at
the end remove this and there we go
now it's all one big if statement else
will execute and none of its upper
components executed so if you have a
hundred else if statements here if none
of them execute then else will execute
at the very end however if one of these
else ifs execute or if this if execute
else will not execute so this will only
execute
only run if
none of the other
if
or L if ran
so this and this did not run then run
else but if this ran skip these if this
ran skip this and skip this all right
now if you run this we'll get you may
not enter if we make them 39 they may
enter if you make them 90 they may not
enter
so it's basically what we had but now
there's less checks and we didn't have
to worry that one if statement will
execute when another should not be
executing because this one has already
executed
it's the same as getting else and then
doing this
instead of having to indent this and do
this we can just do this and I will make
it easier on us as well now let's say we
want to do a few extra checks here let's
say if they may enter you will want to
go
if name is equal to Jack
then 20 off all drinks
and we'll take this
so we're checking if their name is equal
to Jack do this
and then also do this because you have
to remember if something is not part of
an if statement it will still execute if
I go here let's say
echo1
and then I'll go here and say echo2 we
will always see echo1 and Echo 2. no
matter what this if statement says we
will always see this because these are
not part of the if statement
same applies here because this Echo is
not part of this if state if it wants to
be it needs to be indented
because this here is its own little
block scope same with this this is its
own block scope so if we were to go like
this then now this will be part of this
if statement and this if statement is
part of this else statement but they are
not part of this core code here
indentation is very important again
because this indentation says if
something is part of something else
this also shows you you can have an if
statement inside of another if statement
even up here we could say
if name is equal to Jack this could be a
special case
and then
Echo
you may
enter
you are a good customer there we go
so you can have an if statement within
another if statement now if we were to
run this we will get you may enter you
are a good customer and we'll still get
2 here because 2 and we'll just resize
this because 2 is still part of the
normal code it's not part of this if
statement if you were to indent it it
will be part of the if statement and it
will not run
all right but you'll notice we still get
your elderly may not enter
what we want to do here maybe is we
could say if name
okay so let's try adding a nautical if
it's not equal to Jack
Echo this
else this
so we have an if else in here of course
you could have said equals Jack
and you could do this
so this is if the name is Jack do this
but you could also do not equal so the
name is not equal to Jack do this and
take note of this equal symbol here
this is two equal symbols not one one
will reassign
two will check conditions this is a very
important distinction to make
now if we run this we get you may enter
you are a good customer
and in here we could say
let's say their name was
AC
then they say your elderly may not enter
let's say your name was Jack and they
were
38 so they are allowed to enter
then 30 percent of all drinks and you
may enter we might want to put the human
inter first and then say 20 off of all
drinks just to make it look like there's
actually some order here
if you run this then it will display in
that order
and if their name was not jacked they
will not receive that message to run
this you may enter but not 20 of all
drinks
now let's say if it's someone's birthday
they also get 20 percent of drinks
well if that is the case then we could
say
or birthday is equal to true
so now we're checking is their name Jack
or is their birthday today if it is then
print this so this is again an example
of an or statement
with this Boolean statement here we can
actually just go like this this means if
their name is Jack or if it's their
birthday because this is already true or
false
because going like this
is the same as not having that there
because it will still check if this is a
true value
so you can also do if it's not equal to
true
or if it is equal to false
or you could go or not birthday
not here tells us if this is a false
value then it will be represented as
true if you were to open up an M secret
here
which is a little command line and we
would say let X is equal to true
X is a true Boolean
not
X is false because if something is not
true it is false
not not X would be true because if
something because first here this is
true if it's not true it's false if it's
not false it's true
so not will allow us to flip it around
so if it's true it becomes false if it's
false it becomes true
all right so if your name is Jack or if
it's not their birthday they get 30 off
something you might want to take a look
at
now let's say
the name should either be Jack
or it's their birthday but they cannot
be both
so if I say xor birthday then it either
has to be their birthday or their name
should be Jack but if their name is Jack
and it's their birthday they are not
allowed to have a drink
but if it's their birthday
and their name is not Jack they are
allowed to have a drink for 20 off if
their name is Jack but it's not their
birthday they're allowed time to drive
for 20 percent off if you run this we'll
get what we expect
three percent of all drinks but if we
were to make their birthday false
meaning both of these will be false
then you may enter it will not execute
this
but if your name was Jack they will get
20 off their drinks but if their name is
Jack and it's their birthday
then they will not get 20 off all drinks
now let's say we check if it's their
birthday
and
if your name is equal to
Jack
or their age is more than 30. now this
is a little bit confusing because with
python or what Nim will do here
is Nim will first check is it your
birthday if this is true they will try
and check is their name equal to check
as well if this is true that if this is
true or this is true that's what Nim
will do so Nim will basically first run
this statement here the first statement
it sees so if this is true or if this is
true but in our case let's say we don't
care about this we just want to check
this and I will check if it's their
birthday and their name is Jack or their
age is more than 30. then it will Echo
this
but by default it will not do that so
you will need to use brackets to specify
what you want to be checked first if you
run this we get SAS because this
executed as true
cool now one more thing is you might
want to turn aerator operator
so let's go let's greet is equal to if
birthday
so if it's their birthday
then greed becomes happy birth day
else
welcome
so internet radio operator is when you
have this if statement but it's in one
line and returns a value in this case we
could have gone
VAR great is equal to welcome and then
we could have gone if
birthday then greet is equal to
happy birthday
we could have done this but as you see
now greed needs to be Evar
which you don't necessarily want you
might be like me and you want to stick
with lit as most match as possible
so first greed has to be a war plus this
takes up four lines including the
spacers but it could take a free
but this takes up four lines instead of
one line
and this actually might be a little bit
more difficult to read than this inline
if statement
so you might actually see more use in
having this turnario operator around
then using a normal if statement but
this is up to you if you prefer to use a
ternary operator above a normal if
statement then use it just don't go too
overboard because they become very
difficult to read very fast but with
Basics scenarios like this it is one of
the best things in the world and now we
get happy birthday able to make this
false we will get welcome
cool
and that's the basics on if statement
quite a lot to cover quite a lot to
remember
but I hope you all enjoyed and I will
see you all again in the next Nim
tutorial